Hi, I'm Tim Gipson.
I'm going to talk to you about how to tune up a bandsaw.
Now, the most important thing with a bandsaw is definitely we want to make sure that we've got the right tension on the blade so that it keeps it at the appropriate angle to the table that we're trying achieve.
Now, to keep the right tension on, most of your bandsaws will come with a device such as this.
Now you have various widths of band that you can put on of your blades.
In this particular case we've got a quarter inch blade.
So, you have a tension device back here which has a spring with a red mark on it.
So, in this case we want to make sure that this tension is set so that that red mark on that spring is right at the marking on here.
Now, another way we can check that is when we move our foot out of the way here, we could also press and check the deflection.
And we want to have less than a quarter of an inch of deflection.
So, in this case we can see we've got the proper amount of tension.
Okay.
Next thing we want to do is we want to make sure that the blade is running on the rollers correctly.
So, if we open this door then we have the rollers right here.
And what you want to make sure is you want to make sure the blade is running right on the inside.
Now, if it's not then we can make the adjustment and that would be back here.
In tuning up, keeping our bandsaw working good is to check our base and to make sure that it is perpendicular to the blade.
And in that case we can use a right angle such as this to come in and to check the blade against that.
And then we have adjustments on our table.
Then, finally, and it's very important to make sure that the blade stays the right orientation is that we have our blocks that are in here.
And these are either phenolic blocks or hardwood blocks that are to each side of the blade.
And that keeps that blade from moving back and forth as you're cutting.
And so as those wear down over time you'll want to make sure that you cut new blocks to keep that in there.
So, I'm Tim Gipson and that's how to tune up a bandsaw.